Hello,
so today we're going to be talking
about using media that comes in from the
browser
and the demonstration that I put
together is inspired by this piece of
art by Lisa Yevbrot who teaches at UC Santa Barbara.
She was part of
this group at
San Jose State in the late 80s,
early 90s,
I want to say.
Maybe it was just the 90s,
but is known for an early piece of net art that she did there
called every IP that maps queried every IP address on the
internet and kind of mapping it visually in different ways.
But this piece from 2009 is called
Evidence Days Following Difference.
And it's an honest attempt.
I'm just reading off the screen here to capture a ghost.
These are photographs taken automatically every minute for
five hours during a haunted night accompanied by images
showing the difference between two sequential photographs.
So how do we measure similarity?
How do we measure difference computationally?
There are lots of ways.
It depends on
what we're measuring and how we're doing it.
She continues.
We can never know for sure what happened in the
minute passing between one photograph and the next.
We see differences, traces of activity.
The TV is turned on and off.
The doll is moving.
The cat is lingering.
Even if we choose to believe the
photographs objectively record events,
there is a 59.7 second space in which the
skeptic and the believer must join in doubt.
And then she describes these two prints on the right.
The top one is a composite of all the differences.
And the smaller is a visualization
of exif data about the images size,
compression and color.
So if you click this, you get
detailed pictures from this room.
And you can see what the difference looks like.
It looks like a lot of pixels.
And we get a timestamp.
And so she made this piece five days after the death of her mother.
And yeah,
just using this computational process to think about how we combine,
how we measure.
I
think it's pretty interesting.
And so I sought to make a version of this that would work
in the browser using the camera that's available to it.
Let's pull that up.
And I already see that there's a bug here because it's been like
making these divs outlined here in dark red over and over and over.
I think every,
every few seconds rather than having it run every minute,
every 57.9 seconds.
I think she said her was a 59.7.
I have a question.
I have it going every,
I think,
five seconds because when you're writing code,
it's hard to wait that long when you're testing something.
So I could bump that number up.
Now that it sort of works.
So this is asking permission to use my camera.
You know,
it's great that browsers have these security methods.
Before they can access a microphone or camera,
they have to prompt us apps,
not always so.
But that website.
Yes,
I'm going to say yes.
And it loads right in here.
We can see on the left,
we have this is a video tag that is receiving
the camera through set of JavaScript methods,
get user media.
And then on the right,
we're passing it into a canvas element.
And the canvas element allows us to
both read and write individual pixels.
Over time,
including copying pixels from something else,
whether it's.
Whether it's a video element and image element,
another canvas.
And so as fast as it possibly can,
it's just refreshing this canvas with frames from the video.
The video element is also has some CSS running on it.
That rotates the hue value using CSS filter.
And the reason that I did this is that.
To
show that the effects that we put on to a video,
whether we scale it,
whether we use filter effects from CSS,
they don't actually change the pixel value of what's underneath.
In order to do that,
you'd have to move it into a canvas and then do the effects on that.
And there are filters on that are available to canvas.
But what isn't available to canvas
canvas is the transition property in CSS.
That lets you gradually shift from one to another.
You'd actually have to write your own
timing function that would shift the value.
Over time.
And that's not so hard to do, but
it's not quite as easy as it is with CSS. So just
letting you know.
So with this canvas,
it's every five seconds,
it's making a copy of it.
And then when there are two.
It's layering.
Then together using this difference
operation that shows what changes.
And I think
you'll start to wind up with a bunch of.
Still frames here.
And then we see the difference.
So this is what has changed between one photograph in the next.
And it looks different than.
Then you have Bratz because color is a function in the difference.
Blending mode that I'm using.
I think.
We end up with this much more pixelated black and white in hers.
And I haven't completely accounted for that.
But if I the more still I am the darker the images.
Because it's subtracting.
The. The darker pixel from the lighter
pixel in the comparison for each.
Pixel location.
It's looking at the two images.
And.
Whichever one is a lower number of brightness per channel.
It's subtracting.
From the brighter.
And so if they're equal.
If they're the same value in both.
You get zero.
And we can talk a little bit about the math.
But that's what this does.
It's not quite exactly.
Evidence stays following difference.
But. I thought it would be a.
I think I could example of
bringing user media into the browser.
Oh, here's me.
Touching my face.
Here I'll like wave my wave my hands in front of the screen.
Watch this.
Scrawled out really far now.
Now these images are in the browser.
Yeah,
there we go.
There's some hands.
Catch these hands.
These images are in my web page here.
But they aren't like.
They aren't.
They aren't going anywhere else.
They could.
It's not hard to send images from a website to a server.
And if I was doing that.
That would show up in the network tab here.
As network requests to send the image data to a server.
So just yeah.
So that's that.
Let's look a little bit at the code here.
I think this is a little bit bigger.
So canvases have a border.
Video has this transition.
It's about a quarter of a second.
And I set this is a little bit of a hack.
So we have a video tag with the ID
Vid. We have a canvas with ID camp.
The canvas has a width of 640 and a height of 480,
which happens to be the resolution
of the video coming out of my camera.
I don't know.
Entirely what will happen if you know
somebody with a 1080 camera connects to this.
Maybe you have a fancy high resolution webcam.
You can let me know.
It would be possible to set the canvas with to
the resolution of the incoming get user media.
That would be a smart thing to do.
The way that I set this up is pretty bare bones.
There's a lot of error checking.
And I
think that's the way that I set this up.
So I have this a sig function get media.
And that gets past constraints.
Constraints basically define
do you want audio?
Do you want video?
Do you want both?
And when this function gets called.
It's at stream to null.
And then it tries to set up a script. And then it tries to set the stream to get user media.
The await means it's waiting for the get user media to succeed.
And when it does.
It sets the video source object,
which is different than like video at .src,
which you point to a file.
Source objects can point to other kinds of things like streams.
So the stream gets fed to the video object.
The video player.
And then it starts playing.
If you don't play
the video element,
even when it's getting live media,
it will look like a still image.
And then I call this start rotation function.
And my sense is actually that this await is firing sooner than.
It's not actually waiting for the user to accept.
The permission.
That like it's obviously not getting
the user media until you accept.
I think there's actually something else going on here,
which is why all those boxes are on my screen.
If there are any errors here,
handle the error.
Well, yeah, to do, right.
So I'm calling this function get media
with a video true and audio fall.
So it's not capturing audio.
It didn't ask me to use my microphone.
Then I have this.
When.
And no set interval.
With a nameless function that copies the vid,
which is the ID for the video element to CTX. What is CTX?
CTX is a variable that tells can the canvas.
I'm just using the IDs. I learned this week that
every element that you give an ID exists at
the top level is a variable like I had no idea.
And so saying that this.
And getting the context is the part of the
canvas that you can actually run functions on.
You don't run the functions on the element,
which is what can would be.
You run it on the 2D context of the canvas.
And you're probably wondering,
are there three dimensional contexts?
And there are.
And that's
how things like 3JS and Babylon,
the parts of P5JS that do 3D things.
They run on 3D context of canvas.
Or.
They actually use a 2D canvas and render 3D
using abstractions into 2D. But they exist.
And the
working with 3D methods that are available in the DOM directly.
I feel like is asking to not have a great time.
They're very complicated.
And I. It's one of those situations we're having the abstraction.
Having somebody like simplified the process for you with a library.
Really
comes in handy.
I'm using really just the most basic canvas functions.
In this program.
And then I'm using draw image to copy one element into another.
There are things to draw shapes to draw
text to do like lots of the things.
That you can do in P5JS. And they're a little bit grittier.
Then P5JS. But they're not so bad.
Drawing shapes.
Making a.
Draw loop.
It's not too bad.
And you'll see a little bit of that in the next example.
But. So you'll see that this set interval.
I don't actually pass.
A time to it.
It could be like every fraction of a second,
which you get this kind of.
Stop motion kind of effective.
Like,
you know.
And image every once in a while.
If you don't pass.
An interval time.
It's that interval.
It's just going to run as fast as it can.
And so that's why you're seeing the video look smooth.
And that canvas like.
We up here.
Like it's pretty smooth.
Right. Stupid.
Then here's like this CSS rotation.
I store the degrees of zero over here.
And here I have a set interval for also 220 milliseconds.
The same amount of time it takes to do a.
Transition.
And every time it does that,
it increases the degrees by 10 by 10. And so he rotate.
Use is a color model called HSL hue saturation and.
Chess out.
Is that right?
Hue saturation and lightness.
I think so.
There are different color models.
RGB is probably the one that you've used.
Where you're setting red, green and blue.
Values between zero.
And 255. But there's others.
There's HSL. There's CMYK. Sion magenta yellow and black.
And what's nice about.
HSL or even just you.
Is you can have a pixel and just change the color by changing its.
It's degrees.
It's like 360 degrees of a circle.
And I'm just adding 10. Every quarter of a second.
And.
It doesn't matter that they go over 360. It still knows what to do.
You don't have to worry about resetting it.
And using.
You know,
using operations to do that,
which is nice.
So. It's.
Coping the image.
I don't think I actually need to be copying the image in
this function because it's happening on this other interval.
So I could take that out.
But. Yeah, you know, you write code.
You write bugs.
I do that too.
We have this other.
Set interval and it's fine to have.
Hell is that intervals running.
There's three that we can just see on the page here.
This one.
And this one.
And so the one that runs every second.
Every 1000 milliseconds is doing the snapshot function.
And the snapshot function is creating a div.
Oh, yeah, firmware update.
Go away.
Please, thank you.
It's creating a div.
Parent div for the canvas that goes into
this section that's called snapshots.
And we can see that in the HTML. Yes. Section ID snapshots.
And that's holding all of these.
Both the like the positive images and the difference images.
And so it's creating a new canvas.
This just for screenshots with the same width and height as.
The other images.
What's coming from the video.
I'm constructing an ID so I can target this later with queries.
So this canvas has an ID that's initial
like as in like the positive image.
And then the shot count.
So this the shot count is a.
Number that I'm increasing.
Every time this runs.
And so each.
Initial.
And so this is the first. And then I'm going to. And then I get an ID and each diff gets
an ID. So then I copy from the canvas
at the very top of the screen.
To this new canvas.
Which is the CTX. Using the same draw image function.
And then I make a new.
I add the div.
I add the canvas to our parent div.
Then if shot count.
And what is shot count.
Shot count is this.
This sort of timer here.
This iterator.
If it's zero.
It will like.
In an if statement zero is the same thing as false.
So if there aren't any shots.
Then.
This won't run.
But as soon as there's one.
Which means there's actually a second one because
it only other rates at the end of the loop.
As soon as there's.
And
then this creates a comparison canvas.
For the difference image.
So this makes yet another canvas using great element.
Same coordinates.
Same height and width.
It gets an ID of diff plus shot count.
It also gets a context.
It also gets a copy of. The.
Image be like right next to it.
Which is the see over here gets copied into it.
And then I change.
For the.
The canvas context of.
Of this canvas.
I set the global composite operation.
And. What is that.
So. Here we can see.
Just a little easter egg for you.
Um.
What.
What is the difference?
Um. It subtracts the darker of the two
constituent colors from the lighter color.
Painting with white.
Inverts the backdrop color.
Painting with black produces no change.
And then you get a little bit of the algorithm here.
Which I don't totally rock.
Um. You also get a list of the specification
here for every other blending mode.
Exclusion.
Similar to difference lower in contrast.
It uses this.
Um. You get.
Uh. Soft light.
You get hard light.
You get color.
You can play with these.
Um. I encourage it.
These should be familiar to you if you've used Photoshop or.
They are the layer of blending modes.
And. They are.
Common and really anything that allows you to mix images together.
Different programs.
Um. Inpliment them with slightly different.
math,
but this is the math that's used for the browser.
Um. So then it's loading the previous image.
So it's copied.
It's copied the positive,
normal looking photograph,
and now it's picking the one before that.
So it's like using a query selector to pick initial,
and then like with an ID of the current ID
minus one.
And then it's copying that.
But because it's copying over an existing image and it's using
this difference composite operation,
that's why it looks the way it does.
So what we're seeing is the
difference between an image taken
just before this operation happens
combined with the image from a second
before that,
or one loop behind that if we were to change the timer.
We append this child,
we append this
child element
to the div,
and then we apply
that entire div to the snapshots section.
And we increase the counter,
and that's the entire program.
So that's how that works.
So once I got this working,
you know,
it doesn't look exactly like you have Brot's piece.
I was like,
oh,
what would the audio equivalent of this be?
Can you subtract?
Like
web audio segments from one another?
Like you can an image of course.
How hard could that be?
And, um,
you might just want to stop the video here,
because this gets kind of complicated.
And I really ended up out in the weeds on this,
because it turns out that working
with audio data is is a lot different. Um,
and quite a bit more complicated than working with pixel data.
But I do want to just show you what I put together
and make it available in case it's useful to you.
Um,
I don't expect this to make entirely a ton of sense to you,
because I honestly ended up copying and pasting
code that I found on stack exchange that I found.
And, uh,
Mozilla, um,
demonstration code and some other places in order to get this
to where it is now.
So, um, let me refresh this.
Uh,
when I press this,
it's going to ask permission for my microphone.
See, yep, here it is.
And we have this little visualizer here.
Who?
Uh,
is it not?
Is it not?
Are we not getting sound?
I wonder.
So every five seconds, it's recording sound,
except for that I'm not getting sound.
Well, that's, I'm just going to end this.
And I'll do another video of this works.
Because now I'm wondering if this has been
recording sound at all during the screen recording.
And I'm going to be so, so,
so annoyed.
If I just recorded all this time.
And got me. And I'm going to be able to do this.
I'm not going to be able to do anything.
Um,
but that is, that is how it is sometimes.